Carolina Power and Light Photograph Collection PHC.68
State Archives of North Carolina
Carolina Power and Light Photograph Collection
1900-1975
PHC.68
This collection consists of 558 folders (many containing multiple items) housing photographic prints and negatives from the photographic library of Carolina Power and Light. The photographs date c. 1900-1975 and are a good source of early 20th century photographs of small towns and cities across North Carolina, especially Raleigh. Photos of small towns and cities depict overall street scenes in downtown areas, important buildings, hotels, retail stores, commercial structures, street cars, automobiles, delivery trucks, and people on the street.
Carolina Power and Light
State Archives of North Carolina
Box Carolina Power and Light Photograph Collection
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by the following series; however, each item within each series has a unique call number and is described individually. Cities: A to Z (except Raleigh); Cities: Raleigh; History: Farms (agriculture); History: Linemen; Transportation; Employees; Mills; Marketing and Advertising; History: Storms; History: Environmental; People; Power Plants; Recreation (includes CP&L sports teams); Research; Scenic; Transmission (electrical lines, etc.); Transportation.
Biographical/Historical
Carolina Power and Light Company (CP&L) was founded 13 July 1908 as the result of a merger between Cape Fear Power Company, Consumer Light and Power Company and Raleigh Electric. Savvy business decisions, such as the company's focus on marketing household electric appliances like refrigerators and electric irons, created a healthy demand for electricity in the late 1910s through the early 1920s. Through the 1920s and 1930s, the company continued to acquire smaller electric companies and add to its service network while also building new infrastructure such as transmission lines and hydroelectric plants-all of which are depicted in this collection.
In addition to private household use of electricity, municipal and industrial use was mainstream by the late 1920's. In the early 1910s, the textile industry in North Carolina started to make a transition from water turbines and steam engines to small electric motors to power the looms and other machinery. CP&L provided much of the power to these industrial giants. Various mills across North Carolina and the electric motors installed are depicted in this collection.
Moving into the 1930's the company gained competition from the federal government after President Franklin D. Roosevelt signed the Tennessee Valley Authority Act which gave the government authority to build hydroelectric power plants. To retain customers during the Great Depression and compete with the government, the company decreased rates-almost 50% over a 7 year period. This tactic proved to be very sucessful and further spread the use of electricity.
During the development of nuclear power in the 1950's, the company sent employees to study at the nuclear reactor on the campus of North Carolina State University. In 1966 the company's first nuclear reactor was finished in Hartsville, SC. North Carolina's first plant in Brunswick County was completed in 1975 and Shearon Harris Nuclear Power Plant in New Hill followed in 1987.
Carolina Power and Light acquired Florida Progress Corporation in 2000 resulting in the formation of Progress Energy. Progress Energy and Duke Energy merged in 2012.
Sources:
McCrea, William J. "Carolina Power & Light Company." NC Pedia. N.p., 2006. Web. 15 Dec. 2015.
A Century of Progress; Celebrating Progress Energy's History of Service. Old Saybrook,: Greenwich Group, 2008. Print.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 558 folders (many containing multiple items) housing photographic prints and negatives from the photographic library of Carolina Power and Light. The photographs date c. 1900-1975 and are a good source of early 20th century photographs of small towns and cities across North Carolina, especially Raleigh. Photos of small towns and cities depict overall street scenes in downtown areas, important buildings, hotels, retail stores, commercial structures, street cars, automobiles, delivery trucks, and people on the street. These photographs are generally very well composed and rendered. The collection is also a good source for exterior and interior images of textile mills, power plants, commercial and industrial buildings. The photographs document the evolution and marketing of electrical infrastructure, electric appliances, kitchen equipment such as stoves and household aids. Other highlights include mid-20th century storm damage from various ice storms, hurricanes and other weather; Carolina Power & Light employees and offices; the history of electricity and its transmission in North Carolina; and scenic views of the state including highways, roads, and powerlines.
Carolina Power and Light Company.
Electricity; Textile Industry; Textile factories; Floods; Hurricanes; Mills; Coal-Fired Power Plants; Electric power distribution; Hydroelectric power; Electric power; Street-railroads; Streetcars
Asheville (N.C.); Raleigh (N.C.); Bath (N.C.); Cape Hatteras National Seashore (N.C.); Carbonton (N.C.); Charlotte (N.C.); Cherokee (N.C.); Dunn (N.C.); Durham (N.C.); Fayetteville (N.C.); Goldsboro (N.C.); Hamlet (N.C.); Henderson (N.C.); Hendersonville (N.C.); Howelsville (N.C.); Kernersville (N.C.); Kill Devil Hills (N.C.); Lake Lure (N.C.); Laurinburg (N.C.); Lumberton (N.C.); Maxton (N.C.); Morehead City (N.C.); New Bern (N.C.); Oxford (N.C.); Raeford (N.C.); Rockingham (N.C.); Roxboro (N.C.); Southport (N.C.); Wadesboro (N.C.); Wilmington (N.C.); Wrightsville Beach (N.C.); Zebulon (N.C.); Wake County (N.C.)
- Asheboro, NC, Various Street Scenes c. 1930. Business District, at Asheboro, Randolph County, North Carolina; Photographs Taken circa 1930., PhC.68.1.1-5; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Street Scene, Pack Square c. 1913. Elevated views of Pack Square, at Asheville, Buncombe County, North Carolina; Photographs Taken 1913., PhC.68.1.2.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Steam Electric Station c. 1926. Exterior View Looking Southeast of the Asheville Steam Electric Station 1925 Extension, at Asheville, Buncombe County, North Carolina; Photograph Taken 25 August 1926., PhC.68.1.3; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Street Scene Views c. 1927 .Two Street Scene Views of Asheville: The First is a View of an Unidentified Traffic Intersection at a Business District; The Second is an Unidentified Traffic Thoroughfare Leading into or out of Town; Both Photographs Taken in Buncombe County, North Carolina, c. 1927., PhC.68.1.4.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Street Car Barn c. 1927-28. Twenty-Five Views of the Beginning to End Construction Phases of the Asheville Street Car Barn; Beginning After the Floods of August, 1927, Through the Roof Collapse, 13 December 1927; Then Weekly Photographs Until the Completion, March, 1928., PhC.68.1.5.1-25; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Patton Avenue After Street Pole Construction c. 1930. Street Scene View Looking Down Patton Avenue After the Street Pole Construction, at Asheville, Buncombe County, North Carolina, 1930., PhC.68.1.6; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, College (Government) Street c. 1925 and 1958. Three Street Scene Views of Government (now College) Street, Showing a Chestnut Pole, 1925, that was Subsequently Replaced in the 1926 Photograph; The 1958 Image was Taken at the Same Spot and Shows Newer Street Lamps, April, 1958., PhC.68.1.7.1-3; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Carolina Power and Light Public Service Building c. 1932 and 1950. Two Exterior Views of the Front of the Carolina Power and Light Company Public Service Building and Surrounding Businesses, at Asheville, Buncombe County, North Carolina; Photographs Taken circa 1932 and 1950., PhC.68.1.8.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Carolina Power and Light Public Service Building c. 1932 and 1950. Three Street Scene Views of Patton Avenue, at Asheville, Buncombe County, North Carolina; Photographs Taken 1937, 1941 and 1947, Respectively., PhC.68.1.10.1-3; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Night Shot of Tunnel Road c. 1958. Night View of Tunnel Road, Shortly After the Installation of New Lighting, Leading into Asheville, Buncombe County, North Carolina; Photograph Taken circa 1958., PhC.68.1.11; Carolina Power and Light
- Asheville, NC, Gas Plant c. 1927. Exterior View of the Asheville Steam Plant, at Asheville, Buncombe County, North Carolina; Photograph circa 1927., PhC.68.1.12; Carolina Power and Light
- Bath, NC, St. Thomas Church c. 1958. Exterior view of Saint Thomas Church built in 1734, the oldest standing church in the state. Bath, Beaufort County, NC. Photograph c. 1958, PhC.68.1.13; Carolina Power and Light
- Beaufort, NC, Joseph Bell House, c. 1971. Exterior view of the front of the Bell house, built 1767, after restoration at Beaufort, Carteret County, NC. Photograph c. 1971., PhC.68.1.14; Carolina Power and Light
- Cape Hatteras, NC, Surf Fishing c. 1956. View of two unidentified people surf fishing at Cape Hatteras, Dare County, NC. c. 1956, PhC.68.1.15; Carolina Power and Light
- Charlotte, NC, East and West Trade Street c. 1923. Two separate street scenes looking east and west down Trade Street in Charlotte, Mecklenburg County, NC c. 1923, PhC.68.1.16.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Cherokee, NC, "Unto These Hills" Dramatization c. 1964. View of the dramatization, "Unto These Hills" performed by the Cherokee Braves on Qualla reservation, at Cherokee, Swain County, NC. c. 1964, PhC.68.1.17; Carolina Power and Light
- Dunn, NC, Unidentified Residential Street c. 1923. Two views of First Baptist Church and an unidentified residence on Broad Street in Dunn, Harnett County, NC, 24 October 1923., PhC.68.1.19.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Clinton, NC, Tree Trimming and Removal c. 1927. Four views of crews trimming and removing trees. Sycamore Street intersection, Clinton, Sampson County, NC c. 1927, PhC.68.1.18.1-4; Carolina Power and Light
- Dunn, NC, Carolina Power and Light Office c. 1923. Three separate views of the exterior of the Carolina Power and Light office. Dunn, Harnett County, NC c. 1923., PhC.68.1.20.1-3; Carolina Power and Light
- Dunn, NC, Carolina Power and Light Office, Interior Views c. 1925. Five separate interior views of the Carolina Power and Light Office. Dunn, Harnett County, NC c. 1925, PhC.68.1.21.1-5; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, Corner Roxboro and Main Streets c. 1915. Elevated view of street at the corner of Roxboro Road and Main Street looking north, Durham, Durham County, NC c. 1915, PhC.68.1.22; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, Main Street c.1923. View of Main Street looking east from Corcoran Street. Shows the Geer Building, Fidelity Bank and First National bank. Durham, Durham County, NC c. 1923, PhC.68.1.23; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, Corner of Main and Corcoran Streets c. 1914. Two street views of the corner of Main and Corcoran Streets. The Trust Building (tallest), the united States Post Office (center) and the Academy of Music. Durham, Durham County, NC c. 1914, PhC.68.1.24.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, Main Street Looking West c. 1912. Main Street looking west in Durham, Durham County, NC c. 1912, PhC.68.1.25; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, East Main Street c. 1912. East Main Street between Corcoran and Mangum Streets. Durham, Durham County, NC c. 1912, PhC.68.1.26; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, American Tobacco Company, Pettigrew Street c. 1920. Exterior front view of the American Tobacco Company World Headquarters Factory. Manufacturers of Bull Durham Smoking Tobacco, Pettigrew Street, Durham, Durham County, NC. c. 1920, PhC.68.1.27; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, Chesterfield Cigarettes Factory c. 1920. Exterior view of the Chesterfield Cigarette Factory, formerly W. Duke and Sons Tobacco Company. Later becomes Liggett and Myers. Main Street, Durham, Durham County, NC c. 1920, PhC.68.1.28; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, Durham High School, Duke Street c. 1925. Exterior view of Durham High School on Duke Street, Durham, Durham County, NC. c. 1925, PhC.68.1.29; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, Watts Hospital c. 1923. Exterior view of campus of Watts Hospital built in 1908. Currently North Carolina School for Science and Math. Club Boulevard and Broad Streets, Durham, Durham County, NC c. 1923, PhC.68.1.30; Carolina Power and Light
- Durham, NC, Residences on Duke Street c. 1920. Two exterior views of residences on Duke Street in Durham, NC. Residences of John Sprut Hill and Harwood Hall, Home of George Watson Watts. Durham, Durham County, NC c. 1920, PhC.68.1.31.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Fayetteville, NC, Hay Street Looking Toward Market House c. 1915. Hay Street looking toward the Old Slave Market House. Fayetteville, Cumberland County, NC c. 1909, PhC.68.1.32; Carolina Power and Light
- Fayetteville, NC, St. Luke's Hospital c. 1910. Front: exterior view of Saint Luke's Hospital. Reverse: exterior view of an unidentified municipal building shortly after construction. Fayetteville, Cumberland County, NC c. 1910, PhC.68.1.33.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Goldsboro, NC, Main Street c. 1870. Elevated view of Main Street business district and railroad yard. Goldsboro, Wayne County, NC c. 1870, PhC.68.1.34.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Goldsboro, NC, Center Street Business District c. 1923. Street view of Center Street business district. People's Bank and Trust Company, Wayne Shoe Store, Bizzell Hay and Feed are seen. Goldsboro, Wayne County, NC c. 1923, PhC.68.1.35.1-3; Carolina Power and Light
- Goldsboro, NC, Business District c. 1928. Street scene of downtown Goldsboro business district. Cars are seen parked along street in front of businesses. c. 1928, PhC.68.1.36; Carolina Power and Light
- Goldsboro, NC, Street Scene c. 1928. Street scene in Goldsboro, NC. Intersection of Walnut Street and John Street looking north up John Street. Pedestrians are seen on a busy sidewalk, cars are seen parked along the street as cars drive by. c. 1928, PhC.68.1.37; Carolina Power and Light
- Goldsboro, NC, Carolina Power and Light Office c. 1925. Two views of the Carolina Power and Light Company office in Goldsboro, NC. One exterior view of the office at the time it moved to 128 South James Street-the old Weil Brothers office. One interior view of the office showing working clerks and electronic goods for sale. c. 1925, PhC.68.1.38.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Goldsboro, NC, Street Scenes c. 1928-1931. Five varying street views of downtown Goldsboro, NC business district. Center and Walnut Streets are seen along with an unidentified street. A man is seen standing at the entrance to Crystal Cafe, looking toward camera, lighting a cigarette. Other views show various businesses, streets lined with cars and pedestrians on sidewalks. Goldsboro, Wayne County, NC. c. 1928-31, PhC.68.1.39.1-5; Carolina Power and Light
- Hamlet, NC, Yadkin River Power Company c. 1910. Two front exterior views of Yadkin River Power Company office, shown at night and during the day. Also included is one interior view of Hamlet office (PhC68.1.40.3) and one interior view of office in Wadesboro, NC (PhC68.1.40.4). c. 1910-1925, PhC.68.1.40.1-4; Carolina Power and Light
- Hamlet, NC, Carolina Power and Light Crew at Yadkin River Power Company c. 1912. A Carolina Power and Light Company Transformer crew is seen posing with a large truck and trailer. Four men are seen standing by the truck and one man behind the trailer parked in front of the Hamlet, NC Yadkin River Power Company office. Hamlet, Richmond County, NC. c. 1912, PhC.68.1.41.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Hamlet, NC, Main Street c. 1912. Main Street in Hamlet, NC is seen looking south east. Residents are seen in the street with horse drawn wagons. Children are seen on the sidewalk and in the street on bicycles. Hamlet, Richmond county, NC c. 1912, PhC.68.1.42.1; Carolina Power and Light
- Hamlet, NC, Champlain (Chamberlain) Street c. 1918. Corner of Champlain (Chamerlain) and Main Streets in Hamlet, NC. The Eli A. Lackey house is seen on the corner as large power poles run down the street. Hamlet, Richmond County, NC, 24 April 1918, PhC.68.1.43; Carolina Power and Light
- Hamlet, NC, Seaboard Air Line Rail Road Station and Hotel c. 1915. View of the Seaboard Air Line Railroad Station in Hamlet, NC. Approximately a dozen people are seen around the front of the station. Railroad tracks are seen in the foreground. Hamlet, Richmond County, NC c. 1915, PhC.68.1.44; Carolina Power and Light
- Henderson, NC, James Street c. 1918. James Street in Henderson, NC is pictured. Houses lining the street and a power pole are seen. Caption reads, "Carolina Power and Light Company 22 K. V. Line on James Street, Henderson, NC May 1919". Henderson, Vance County, NC May 1918, PhC.68.1.45; Carolina Power and Light
- Henderson, NC, James and Garnet Streets. 22 April 1918. Two views of James Street (one view shows automobile) in Henderson, NC and one view Garnet Street. Residential areas are seen with large power poles running down the length of the street. One identical copy with each print. Photos are captioned, "22000 Volt line on Garnet (James) Street Henderson, NC. 4-22-1918". Henderson, Vance County, NC. 22 April 1918, PhC.68.1.46.1-6; Carolina Power and Light
- Henderson, NC, Garnet Street Business District c. 1924. Garnet Street business district. Post office is seen on the right along with various retail establishments on both sides of the streets. Automobiles are seen parked along street with some pedestrians waking past. Henderson, Vance County, NC c. 1924, PhC.68.1.47; Carolina Power and Light
- Henderson, NC, Garnet Street at Night c. 1934. View of Garnet Street business district in Henderson, NC at night. Cars are seen parked along the street as street lights illuminate the area. Henderson, Vance County, NC c. 1934, PhC.68.1.48; Carolina Power and Light
- Henderson, NC, Carolina Power and Light Serviceman With His Truck c. 1925. Carolina Power and Light Serviceman, Frederick (Fritz) W. Daeke (1888-1957) is seen posing beside his service truck, a Corbitt Model B. Henderson, Vance County, NC. c. 1925 PhC68.1.273 is a duplicate of this print., PhC.68.1.49; Carolina Power and Light
- Hendersonville, NC, Night View U.S. Hwys 70 and 74 Business c. 1957. Night view of US Highways 70 and 74 business at night. Amoco, Esso, Gulf, Shell, Holiday Inn, and McDonald's can be seen as cars travel down the road. Hendersonville, Henderson County, NC c. 1957, PhC.68.1.50.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Kernersville, NC Highway 66 Business District c. 1940. Kernersville, NC street scene. Central Hotel is seen on far right as people are seen walking down sidewalks, roadwork is seen in foreground. Kernersville, Forsyth County, NC c. 1940, PhC.68.1.51; Carolina Power and Light
- Kill Devil Hills, NC, Wright Brothers Memorial c, 1935, 1969. Two tourists are seen observing the Wright Brothers Memorial in Kill Devil Hills, NC c. 1935 Also included is an interior view of a reproduction of the original Wright Brothers plane produced by NC Dept of Natural and Economic Resources c. 1969. Kill Devil Hills, Dare County, NC., PhC.68.1.52.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Lake Lure, NC, Views of Dam and Scenic Views c. 1927. One scenic view of Lake Lure looking toward an island on the lake and mountains in the far distance. Two views of a newly finished Lake Lure dam. A crowd of people are seen on top of the dam (possibly dedication). Lake Lure, Rutherford County, NC March 1927, PhC.68.1.53.1-3; Carolina Power and Light
- Laurinburg, NC, State Bank of Laurinburg c. 1909. The State Bank building in Laurinburg, NC is seen. Three men are seen sitting in a window near a horse drawn carriage parked on the street. Laurinburg, Scotland County, NC c. 1909, PhC.68.1.54.1; Carolina Power and Light
- Long Beach, NC, Aerial Views c. 1938 and 1954. Two aerial views of Long Beach, NC. The first was taken at an altitude of ~500ft c. 1938. The second was taken at an altitude of ~1000 feet 15 October 1954 just after Hurricane Hazel. Long Beach, Brunswick County, NC, PhC.68.1.55.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Lumberton, NC, Business District, 24 October 1923. Five identical prints of varying quality of the intersection of North Elm and West 5th Street in Lumberton, NC. Businesses, people and cars line the street. Lumberton, Robeson County, NC 24 October 1923, PhC.68.1.56.1-5; Carolina Power and Light
- Lumberton, NC, Robeson County Courthouse c. 1907 and 1920. Two views of the Robeson County Courthouse in Lumberton, NC. One view was taken in 1907 and the other in 1920. Lumberton, Robeson County, NC c. 1907 and 1920, PhC.68.1.57.1-2; Carolina Power and Light
- Maxton, NC, Construction of Female College c. 1910. Carolina College (Presbyterian Junior College for Boys) is seen under construction. Bricks and building materials surround a partially completed structure covered in wood scaffolding. Maxton, Robeson County, NC c. 1910, PhC.68.1.58; Carolina Power and Light
- Morehead City, NC, Fort Macon Aerial c. 1950. Aerial view of Fort Macon on the Outer Banks of North Carolina. Carteret County, NC c. 1950, PhC.68.1.59; Carolina Power and Light
- New Bern, NC, Elevated Views of Tryon Palace c. 1963. Three identical prints of the courtyard, gardens and front exterior of Tryon Palace. New Bern, Craven County, NC c. 1963, PhC.68.1.60.1-3; Carolina Power and Light
- New Bern, NC, Local Carolina Power and Light Office. c. 1954. Exterior view of the Carolina Power and Light company office in Newbern, NC. A man and a woman are seen walking away front the front door. Newbern, Craven County, NC. c. 1954, PhC.68.1.61; Carolina Power and Light
- Oxford, NC, Interior View of Carolina Power and Light Office c. 1914. Interior view of the Carolina Power and Light office in Oxford, Granville County, NC c. 1914, PhC.68.1.62; Carolina Power and Light
- Oxford, NC, Business District c. 1914. Hillsboro Street in Oxford, NC is shown looking east. A hotel is seen on the right and Blalock Motor Company is seen on the right. Businesses and cars are seen lining the street. Oxford, Granville County, NC c. 1914, PhC.68.1.63; Carolina Power and Light
- Raeford, NC, Electric Lines/Street Scenes, Business District c. 1927. Five small snapshots of areas in and around the business district of Raeford, NC. 64.1 shows a side street with a Ford dealership in the near background and cars lining the right side of the street. 64.2 shows electrical lines and a streetlight. 64.3 shows parked cars along an unidentified street. A business, W. A. Gregory's can be seen. 64.4 shows a residential street with a service station in the near distance. 64.5 shows a young girl and a woman crossing a side street. Print is captioned "Bishops Crook, Raeford". Raeford, PhC.68.1.64.1-5; Carolina Power and Light
- Rockingham, NC, Yadkin River Power Company Storefront c. 1912. Storefront of the Yadkin River Power Company Local Office in Rockingham, NC shown at night. Lighting products can be seen displayed in the windows. Rockingham, Richmond County, NC c. 1912, PhC.68.1.65; Carolina Power and Light
- Rockingham, NC, Washington Street Looking East c. 1924. Washington Street in Rockingham, NC is shown looking east. Businesses, cars, and people are seen lining the street. Rockingham, NC, Richmond County, NC c. 1924, PhC.68.1.66; Carolina Power and Light
- Rockingham, NC, Bank of Pee Dee c. 1912. Bank of Pee Dee on the corner of Washington and Hancock Streets in Rockingham, NC is seen. Rockingham, Richmond County, NC c. 1912, PhC.68.1.67; Carolina Power and Light